A Guide to the Association for Women in Architecture Records, 1928-2000
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Association for Women in Architecture Records, 1928-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1988-022
15 cu. ft. 10 boxes
The Association for Women in Architecture (AWA) was originally founded in 1922 as Alpha Alpha Gamma, a national sorority for women architecture students. In 1934, the alumnae of the sorority formed the Association of Women in Architecture (AWA) as an organization for professional women architects. Today (2017) the AWA exists only through its Los Angeles chapter, with a membership of approximately 200 women architects and designers in the Los Angeles area, with members-at-large across the country. In 1975, the AWA altered its name to the Association FOR Women in Architecture. Records include committee reports, correspondence, membership forms and rosters, photographs, scrapbooks, treasurer's files, and newsletters.
Association for Women in Architecture (U.S.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Association for Women in Architecture Records were donated to Special Collections in June 1988. Additional materials were donated in August 1989 and February 2016.
Historical Note
The Association for Women in Architecture (AWA) was originally founded in 1922 as Alpha Alpha Gamma, a national sorority for women architecture students. In 1934, the alumnae of the sorority formed the Association of Women in Architecture (AWA) as an organization for professional women architects. Its first president was H. Mae Steinmesch of St. Louis, Missouri. Subsequent presidents included Jean Driskel, Virginia Tanzmann, and Vicki Carter.
Although chapters were formed in other cities, the Los Angeles, California, chapter was the most active. In 1964, the national organization dissolved and the other chapters gradually disappeared. The Los Angeles chapter, with a membership of approximately 200 women architects and designers in the Los Angeles area with members-at-large across the country is the only surviving original chapter. In 1975, the AWA altered its name to the Association FOR Women in Architecture.
The organization has had many name iterations over the years some not mentioned above include: The Association of Women in Architecture and Allied Arts (AWA), 1948, and its current form adopted in 2012 Association for Women in Architecture + Design (AWA+ D).
The AWA holds annual meetings, gives out scholarships to women architecture students, and acts as a clearinghouse for information about women's status in the field of architecture.
Scope and Content
The records of the Association for Women in Architecture include committee reports, convention materials, event posters and invitations, photographs, presidents files, membership rosters, constitution and bylaws, correspondence, and videotapes. The bulk of materials relate to the Los Angeles chapter, but the records also include documentation of the national organization and affiliated chapters. Following the original order in which the records were arranged, the materials reflect a loosely chronological order. The photographs, slides, videotapes, and posters are filed at the end of the main administrative files.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged according to the original order compiled by the AWA, which grouped related records together and identified each box by date range.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Association for Women in Architecture(U.S.); Association for Women in Architecture and Design (U.S.)
Occupations:
Architects
Local Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Contents List
- Administrative Files, 1928-1988.
  - 1928-1979.
    - Convention minutes, 1928-1936. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - An Original Watercolor Sketch: The Architect's Recreation,1930. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Alpha Alpha Gamma, 1930-1939. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Treasurer's notes, 1939-1953. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Convention minutes, 1940-1948. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Keystone of Alpha Alpha Gamma, 1943-1951. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Rosters, 1949-1979. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, 1950-1952. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Convention minutes, 1950-1956. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Arch Chapter bulletins, 1950-1962. (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Handbook of Procedure of the AWA and Its Undergraduate Affiliate AAG, 1951. (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, etc., 1952-1954. (Box-folder 1:13)
    - National Directory, 1952-1958. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Student Advisory Committee--Employment in the field of architecture, 1953-1957. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Treasurer's files, 1954. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, etc., 1954-1956. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Advertising for AWA, 1935. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - "Keystone" of Alpha Alpha Gamma, 1954-1964. (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, etc., 1956-1957. (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1956-1958. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Slides of Exhibit at the Los Angeles County Fair, 1956-1959. (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Miscellaneous Handbook Material, 1956-1962. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, etc., 1957-1958. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Convention minutes, 1958-1966. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Membership Applications, 1958-1976. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, membership lists, etc., 1958-1959. (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Professional Handbook, 1958-1962. (Box-folder 1:27)
    - AWA Officers and Committee Chairpersons Records, 1958-1971. (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Master Expansion Manual, 1959. (Box-folder 1:29)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, etc., 1959-1960. (Box-folder 1:30)
    - Student Advisory Project--Employment Opportunities for Women in Architecture, 1959-1960. (Box-folder 1:31)
    - Handbook drafts, 1959-1961. (Box-folder 1:32)
    - Placement Aid Survey, 1960-1961. (Box-folder 1:33)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, notes, etc., 1960-1961. (Box-folder 1:34)
  - 1960-1981.
    - National Directory, 1960-1966. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1960-1968. (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Resolution to Simplify Organization, 1961. (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Student Advisory Project--Employment Opportunities in Architecture for Women, 1961. (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, notes, etc., 1961-1962. (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, Treasurer's notes, etc., 1962-1963. (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, etc., 1963-1964. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Scholarship material, 1963-1971. (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's notes, etc., 1964-1965. (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Lambda Chapter of Alpha Alpha Gamma (University of Kansas), 1964-1976. (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's notes, notes, etc., 1965-1966. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Treasurer's notes, 1965-1971. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, Treasurer's reports, etc., 1966-1967. (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Flyers, clippings from scrapbook, 1966-1981. (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, Treasurer's reports, etc., 1967-1968. (Box-folder 2:15)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, Treasurer's reports, etc., 1968-1969. (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Report of the Second International Congress of Women Architects (UIFA), 1969. (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Meeting minutes, corresondence, Treasurer's reports, notes, etc., 1969-1971. (Box-folder 2:18)
    - Newsletter, 1969-1980. (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Student Advisory Comittee--Employment Opportunities in Architecture for Women, 1970-1975. (Box-folder 2:20)
    - Newsletters, 1970-1979. (Box-folder 2:21)
    - Los Angeles Trade-Technical College Plaque to AWA, 1971. (Box-folder 2:22)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, memos, etc., 1971-1974. (Box-folder 2:23)
    - UIFA Congresses, 1972-1979. (Box-folder 2:24)
    - Roster of Soroptimist Club of Los Angeles, 1973-1974. (Box-folder 2:25)
    - Articles, flyers, and other literature about women in architecture, 1973-1976. (Box-folder 2:26)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, notes, etc., 1974-1975. (Box-folder 2:27)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1974-1975. (Box-folder 2:28)
    - American Institute of Architects Publications about career planning, 1974-1981. (Box-folder 2:29)
    - AIA: Affirmative Action Plan for the Integration of Women in the Architectural Profession, 1975. (Box-folder 2:30)
    - History and list of founding members of the AWA, 1975. (Box-folder 2:31)
  - 1975-1985.
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, Treasurer's reports, etc., 1975-1976. (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Prospective Members, 1975-1976. (Box-folder 3:2)
    - News clippings, info about the status of women in architecture, 1975-1977. (Box-folder 3:3)
    - President's files (folder 1 of 2), 1975-1980. (Box-folder 3:4)
    - President's files (folder 2 of 2), 1975-1980. (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Job Survey Information for Architectural Students, 1976. (Box-folder 3:6)
    - -Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, notes, etc., 1976-1979. (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Brentwood-Pacific Palisades Community Plan, 1977. (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Publicity, 1977-1978. (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Articles, flyers, and other literature about women in architecture, 1977-1979. (Box-folder 3:10)
    - Publicity, 1978-1979. (Box-folder 3:11)
    - International Union of Women Architects Congress in Seattle, WA, 1979. (Box-folder 3:12)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, Treasurer's reports, etc., 1979-1980. (Box-folder 3:13)
    - Christmas party, 1980. (Box-folder 3:14)
    - Prospective Members, 1980. (Box-folder 3:15)
    - Scholarship Material, 1980. (Box-folder 3:16)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, notes, etc., 1980-1981. (Box-folder 3:17)
    - Board meetings, 1980-1982. (Box-folder 3:18)
    - News clippings, 1980-1982. (Box-folder 3:19)
    - National membership directory, 1980-1984. (Box-folder 3:20)
    - Newsletters, "Perspectives," 1980-1985. (Box-folder 3:21)
    - Bylaws and membership list, 1981. (Box-folder 3:22)
    - Newsletter, 1981. (Box-folder 3:23)
    - "Women Up Front '81," 1981. (Box-folder 3:24)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's notes, etc., 1981-1982. (Box-folder 3:25)
  - 1981-1986.
    - Membership list, 1981-1982. (Box-folder 4:1)
    - Membership file, 1981-1982. (Box-folder 4:2)
    - Membership card file, 1981-1982. (Box-folder 4:3)
    - Rosters, 1981-1986. (Box-folder 4:4)
    - Certificate of the National Association of Women in Construction, 1982. (Box-folder 4:5)
    - General correspondence,1982. (Box-folder 4:6)
    - Nominating committee report, 1982. (Box-folder 4:7)
    - Membership correspondence, 1982. (Box-folder 4:8)
    - Handbook, 1982. (Box-folder 4:9)
    - "Women Up Front '82" (folder 1 of 6), 1982. (Box-folder 4:10)
    - "Women Up Front '82" (folder 2 of 6), 1982. (Box-folder 4:11)
    - "Women Up Front '82" (folder 3 of 6), 1982. (Box-folder 4:12)
    - "Women Up Front '82" (folder 4 of 6), 1982. (Box-folder 4:13)
    - "Women Up Front '82" (folder 5 of 6), 1982. (Box-folder 4:14)
    - "Women Up Front '82" (folder 6 of 6), 1982. (Box-folder 4:15)
    - "Women Up Front '82"--stamps, 1982. (Box-folder 4:16)
    - "Women Up Front '82"--logo competition, 1982. (Box-folder 4:17)
    - "Women Up Front '82"--Women in Design Program, 1982. (Box-folder 4:18)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, etc., 1982-1983. (Box-folder 4:19)
    - Budget/Financial Report, 1982-1983. (Box-folder 4:20)
    - Bylaws/Handbooks, 1982-1983. (Box-folder 4:21)
    - Photographs, 1982-1983, and undated. (Box-folder 4:22)
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1982-1983. (Box-folder 4:23)
    - Membership status reports, 1982-1984. (Box-folder 4:24)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, Treasurer's reports, notes, etc., 1983-1984. (Box-folder 4:25)
    - Membership list, report, 1983-1984. (Box-folder 4:26)
    - Bills, financial matters, 1983-1984. (Box-folder 4:27)
    - Greetings to AWA by Tom Bradley (mayor of Los Angeles), 1984. (Box-folder 4:28)
    - 1984 Conference (folder 1 of 4), 1984. (Box-folder 4:29)
    - 1984 Conference (folder 2 of 4). (Box-folder 4:30)
    - 1984 Conference (folder 3 of 4). (Box-folder 4:31)
  - 1984-1988.
    - 1984 Conference (folder 4 of 4). (Box-folder 5:1)
    - 1984 Conference--Steering Committee. (Box-folder 5:2)
    - 1984 Conference--Program Committee. (Box-folder 5:3)
    - 1984 Conference--Program Committee. (Box-folder 5:4)
    - 1984 Conference--Managing Committee. (Box-folder 5:5)
    - 1984 Conference--Fund raising committee. (Box-folder 5:6)
    - 1984 Conference--Public Relations and Communications. (Box-folder 5:7)
    - 1984 Conference--Mailing list. (Box-folder 5:8)
    - Membership brochure request, 1984. (Box-folder 5:9)
    - Scholarship Application forms, 1984. (Box-folder 5:10)
    - Meeting minutes, correspondence, notes, Treasurer's reports, etc., 1984-1985. (Box-folder 5:11)
    - Roster information sheets, 1984-1985. (Box-folder 5:12)
    - Expired members forms, 1984-1985. (Box-folder 5:13)
    - Membership renewal forms, 1984-1985. (Box-folder 5:14)
    - Dues paid (A-K), 1984-1985. (Box-folder 5:15)
    - Dues paid (L-Z), 1984-1985. (Box-folder 5:16)
    - Board of Directors, 1985. (Box-folder 5:17)
    - Officer's Ballot, 1985-1986. (Box-folder 5:18)
    - Membership renewal forms, 1986. (Box-folder 5:19)
    - Newsletters, 1986-1987. (Box-folder 5:20)
    - Correspondence, 1987. (Box-folder 5:21)
    - Membership renewal forms, 1987. (Box-folder 5:22)
    - Membership list, 1988. (Box-folder 5:23)
    - AWA Newsletters, 1990-1992. (Box-folder 5:24)
    - Annual Scholarship Award forms. (Box-folder 5:25)
    - Undergraduate Handbook. (Box-folder 5:26)
    - National Treasurer and National Finance Chair. (Box-folder 5:27)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box-folder 5:28)
    - H. Mae Steinmesch. (Box-folder 5:29)
    - Stationery, Daybook calendar. (Box-folder 5:30)
    - "Architectural Drafting" by Elizabeth Boytor. (Box-folder 5:31)
    - "Jean Driskel--in Memoria". (Box-folder 5:32)
  - 1960-2000
    - 1960s (General, Los Angeles Chapter) (Box-folder 7:1)
    - 1960s (Prospective/New Members) (Box-folder 7:2)
    - 1960s (Prospective/Transfer Members) (Box-folder 7:3)
    - 1960s (Former Members) (Box-folder 7:4)
    - 1960s (Reports) (Box-folder 7:5)
    - 1960s (Old Rosters) (Box-folder 7:6)
    - 1960s (Outdated manual and forms) (Box-folder 7:7)
    - 1960s (General, National and Other Chapters) (Box-folder 7:8)
    - 1960s (Newsletters, National) (Box-folder 7:9)
    - 1960s (Leadership Manual) (Box-folder 7:10)
    - 1971-1972 (Box-folder 7:11)
    - 1976-1977 (folder 1 of 2) (Box-folder 7:12)
    - 1976-1977 (folder 2 of 2) (Box-folder 7:13)
    - 1977-1978 (Box-folder 7:14)
    - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 7:15)
    - 1979-1980 (Box-folder 7:16)
    - 1981-1982 (folder 1 of 4) (Box-folder 7:17)
    - 1981-1982 (folder 2 of 4) (Box-folder 7:18)
    - 1981-1982 (folder 3 of 4) (Box-folder 7:19)
    - 1981-1982 (folder 4 of 4) (Box-folder 7:20)
    - 1982-1983 (Meeting Log-Book) (Box-folder 7:21)
    - 1982-1983 (General) (Box-folder 7:22)
    - 1982-1983 (AWA Minutes) (Box-folder 7:23)
    - 1982-1983 (AWA Programs) (Box-folder 7:24)
    - 1983-1984 (Box-folder 8:1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box-folder 8:2)
    - 1984-1985 (General) (Box-folder 8:3)
    - 1984-1985 (Designing the Future Conference) (Box-folder 8:4)
    - 1984-1985 (AWA President's Notebook) (Box-folder 8:5)
    - 1984-1985 (AWA President's Notebook) (Box-folder 8:6)
    - 1985-1986 (Box-folder 8:7)
    - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 8:8)
    - 1987-1988 (General) (Box-folder 8:9)
    - 1987-1988 (General) (Box-folder 8:10)
    - 1987-1988 (Gingerbread House Event) (Box-folder 8:11)
    - 1987-1988 (Newsletters, June 1987-July 1988) (Box-folder 8:12)
    - 1987-1988 (Agenda & Minutes, September 1987-August 1988) (Box-folder 8:13)
    - 1988-1989 (General) (Box-folder 8:14)
    - 1988-1989 (General) (Box-folder 8:15)
    - 1988-1989 (California Project, January 27-29, 1989) (Box-folder 8:16)
    - 1988-1989 (Newsletters, August 1988-June 1989) (Box-folder 8:17)
    - 1989-1990 (Pearl Brickman Info) (Box-folder 8:18)
    - 1989-1990 (General) (Box-folder 8:19)
    - 1989-1990 (General) (Box-folder 8:20)
    - 1989-1990 (Newsletters) (Box-folder 9:1)
    - 1989-1990 (CWED Conf in San Diego, Feb. 1990) (Box-folder 9:2)
    - 1990-1991 (General) (Box-folder 9:3)
    - 1990-1991 (Newsletters) (Box-folder 9:4)
    - 1990-1991 (Photographs) (Box-folder 9:5)
    - 1991-1992 (Newsletters) (Box-folder 9:6)
    - 1991-1992 (General) (Box-folder 9:7)
    - 1991-1992 (CWED Conference negatives) (Box-folder 9:8)
    - 1991-1992 (CWED Exhibit) (Box-folder 9:9)
    - 1991-1992 (CWED Conference) (Box-folder 9:10)
    - 1991-1992 (CWED Conference) (Box-folder 9:11)
    - 1992-1993 (General) (Box-folder 9:12)
    - 1992-1993 (General) (Box-folder 9:13)
    - 1992-1993 (Photographs) (Box-folder 9:14)
    - 1992-1993 (Newsletters) (Box-folder 9:15)
    - 1993-1994 (General) (Box-folder 9:16)
    - 1993-1994 (Newsletters) (Box-folder 9:17)
    - 1993-1994 (Photographs) (Box-folder 9:18)
    - AWA Retreat 1994 (Box-folder 9:19)
    - AWA Retreat 1994 (Box-folder 9:20)
    - 1994-1995 (General) (Box-folder 9:21)
    - 1996-1997 (General) (Box-folder 9:22)
    - 1996-1997 (General) (Box-folder 10:1)
    - Newsletters and Invitations, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 10:2)
    - Stationery Samples (Box-folder 10:3)
    - Membership Brochures (Box-folder 10:4)
    - Rosters (Box-folder 10:5)
    - Rosters (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Corporate Records
    - AWA Financial (1984) (Box-folder 10:7)
    - Articles and Exemptions (1982-1989) (Box-folder 10:8)
    - By-Laws and Handbook (1983-1984) (Box-folder 10:9)
- Photographs and tapes, 1968-1983.
  - Exhibition photographs, "Architectural Careers for Women," 1968. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Photographs for "Emerging Issues: Women in Environmental Design," 1975. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Mae Steinmesch Designs. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Photographs, 1969-1983. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Negatives Cassette Tape--"A Way of Life, not just a job. Part I". (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Video Tapes. (Box 6)
  - Posters used for exhibitions and awards. (Box 6)
  - Event Posters, 1988-1991, n.d. (Oversize Folder 1)
  - 1989 Women in Architecture, AIA/AWA Exhibit, "A Southern California Perspective" [VHS] (Box-folder 10:10)
  - Slides, 1989 (Box-folder 10:11)